Guide to the Erwin Ramsdell Goodenough Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Erwin Ramsdell Goodenough papers
1896-1969
MS 723
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.75
(38 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, lectures, research notes, correspondence, personal papers and photographs possibly used in some of his publications. The largest part of the papers is comprised of research materials and manuscript drafts for Erwin Goodenough's major work, Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (published 1953-1965), as well as materials relating to The Politics of Philo Judaeus: Practice and Theory.
Goodenough, Erwin Ramsdell, 1893-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Erwin Ramsdell Goodenough, 1961; Cynthia G. Goodenough, 1975, 1978, 1995; Thomas Kraabel, 2003, and John D. Gordan, III, 2010, 2012; Semitic Museum, Harvard University, 2012.
Biographical / Historical
Erwin R. Goodenough, educator, received a B.A. degree from Hamilton College in 1915. He was a student at Drew Theological Seminary from 1915 to 1916, and received his S.T.B. from Garrett Biblical Institute in 1917. Goodenough studied at Harvard for three years until 1920, and received a D.Phil. degree from Oxford University in 1923. He was an instructor of history at Yale, 1923-1926; assistant professor, 1926-1931; associate professor, 1931-1934; professor of history of religion, 1934-1959; the John A. Hoober professor of religion, 1959-1962; and professor emeritus, 1962-1965.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, lectures, research notes, correspondence, personal papers and photographs possibly used in some of his publications. The largest part of the papers is comprised of research materials and manuscript drafts for Erwin Goodenough's major work, Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (published 1953-1965), as well as materials relating to The Politics of Philo Judaeus: Practice and Theory.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Jews -- History -- 168 B.C.-135 A.D; Judaism -- History -- Post-exilic period, 586 B.C.-210 A.D; Clergy; Historians; Goodenough, Erwin Ramsdell, 1893-1965; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History; Yale University. Department of Religious Studies
- Inventory
  - 1961 Accession
    - Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period [manuscript] (Box 1)
    - Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period [manuscript] (Box 1A)
    - Manuscripts and writings (Box 2)
    - Short manuscripts and lectures (Box 2A)
    - Short manuscripts and lectures (Box 3)
    - Short manuscripts and lectures (Box 4)
    - Short manuscripts and lectures (Box 5)
    - Manuscripts and notes for Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (Box 6)
    - Manuscripts and notes for Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (Box 7)
    - Manuscripts and notes for Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (Box 7A)
    - Manuscripts and notes for Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period, volumes 4-7 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence, 1930s-1960s (Box 9)
  - 1974 & 1978 Accessions
    - Correspondence, 1951-1969
      - A-B (Box 10)
      - C-P (Box 11)
      - Q-Z (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous papers, including chapters of book on Jewish Symbols in the Greco-Roman Period (Box 13)
    - Legal, financial and personal papers (Box 14)
    - Legal, financial and personal papers (Box 15)
- Additional Material, 1959-1966; Accession 1995-M-215
  - Religious Perspective [Harper & Brothers, Publishers], 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reviews of books written by Goodenough, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speeches/lectures [mostly arrangements materials], 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Writings
    - "Agnostic Religion": Introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Autobiography [notes], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Bible as Product of The Ancient World", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chapter drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 8 - 13)
    - "An Early Christian Bread Stamp" [includes correspondence about the article], 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Encyclopaedia Judaica, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Evolutionary Ethics", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Galatians", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Greek Garments on Jewish Heroes in the Dura Synagogue [Lown Institute lecture], undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Judaism of the Dura Synagogue", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The Nature of Love in Plato and Freud", undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "The Perspective of Acts" [for Schubert Festschrift], 1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Socrates of History and the Socratic Tradition", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "The State of Israel", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Symbols of the Future: the Question Mark", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Types of Religious Experiences", undated (Box 2, Folder 25 - 27)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 28 - 29)
    - Unpublished, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Photocopy of handwritten will, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-078
  - Philo of Alexandria [seven volumes; work text of Goodenough], 1896-1930 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Circa 1928-1939; Accession 2011-M-015
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of eleven bound volumes of material, titled Philo, relating to Goodenough's book The Politics of Philo Judaeus: Practice and Theory and two bound volumes containing the original handwritten manuscript and the typescript of Jurisprudence of the Jewish Courts of Egypt, done in collaboration with Howard Lehman Goodhart.
  This accession includes volumes II-XII of Philo. Volume I is included in accession 2013-M-019. Volumes II-V, VIII-X contain book by book bibliographical information with occasional photographs of a page; volumes III and V also have some correspondence concerning acquisition of information interspersed. Volume VII consists of correspondence with Dr. Foakes-Jackson, a collaborator who withdrew from the project, and some bibliographical essays (one of which appears twice in other volumes). Volume VI contains the corrected page proofs and Volume XI is the typescript of the book. Volume XII contains post-publication correspondence, primarily addressed to Howard Goodhart, concerning things such as reviews, book distribution, and appreciation.
  - Philo, volumes II-IV, Circa 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Philo, volumes V-VI, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Philo, volumes VII-VIII, Circa 1935-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Philo, volumes IX-X, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Philo, volumes XI-XII, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - The Jurisprudence of the Jewish Courts in Egypt at the Time of the Early Roman Empire as Described by Philo Judaeus, Circa 1928
    - Original manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typescript (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2012-M-047
  This accession consists of nine boxes of brief, general lecture notes hand-written on 3x5 index cards. Topics include: church and state, philosophy, psychology of religion, Justin Martyr and the Reformation. Box 10 consists of one folder of correspondence (two letters and a postcard), one folder of negatives and three folders of photographs with notes.
  - Lectures
    - General
      - C, Undated (Box 1)
      - C-G, Undated (Box 2)
      - G-P, Undated (Box 3)
      - P [philosophy], Undated (Box 4)
      - P [psychology of religion], Undated (Box 5)
      - P-Q, Undated (Box 6)
    - Topical
      - Justin Martyr, Undated (Box 7)
      - Justin Martyr, Undated (Box 8)
      - Reformation, Undated (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1962 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Negatives, Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
- Additional Material, 1935; Accession 2013-M-019
  This accession consists volume I of Philo, which gathers together material related to Goodenough's book The Politics of Philo Judaeus: Practice and Theory. Volumes II-XII of Philo form part of the materials included in accession 2011-M-015. Volume I consists of a typewritten bibliography of manuscripts, books, and articles related to the work of the Philo Judaeus. Many entries in the bibliography include detailed physical descriptions of individual works. The volume also includes an alphabetized index. Handwritten notes in Greek appear throughout the volume.
  - Philo, volume I, 1935 (Box 1, Box system_indicator_99fe9ab7545f32606778a2da7f65464a)